There are many ways that machine learning algorithms can
純粋に予測に対するデータ主導アプローチとして使用できる
be used in purely data driven approaches for prediction.
機械学習アルゴリズムはたくさんあります
Since you already went through a machine learning class,
皆さんは既に機械学習の講義を終えていますので
we won't go into these techniques in too much detail.
この技術の詳細は省きます
But in this video,
このビデオでは
I would like to show you one example that is representative
1 つの例をお見せしたいと思います
of what these algorithms are good at...
このアルゴリズムの得意分野 トラジェクトリークラスタリングです
As is the case with all data driven prediction techniques,
すべてのデータ主導予測技術と同様に
there will be two phases.
2 つのフェーズがあります
An offline training phase where the algorithm learns a model from data
アルゴリズムがデータからモデルを学習するオフライントレーニングフェーズと
and online prediction phase where it uses that model to generate predictions.
モデルを使って予測を作成するオンライン予測フェーズです
Let's discuss the offline phase first.
まず オフラインフェーズについてお話しましょう
The first step is to get a lot of data which you
最初のステップは 静止カメラを交差点に置くなどして
might do by placing a static camera at an intersection.
多量のデータを集めます
Then, we have to clean the data since some of the cars we
観測している車が妨げられたり 処理ステップがうまくいかない場合があるので
observe may be occluded or something else went wrong in the processing step.
データをクリーン処理する必要があります
So we need to discard the bad data.
そこで不良データを除去します
Once the data is gathered and cleaned up,
データを集めてクリーンアップ処理を実行すると
we would be left with a bunch of trajectories that look something like this.
多くのトラジェクトリーが このような形で残ります
Next, we need to define some mathematical measure of
次にトラジェクトリーの類似性を数学的尺度で定義することが必要です
trajectory similarity and there are many ways to do this but intuitively we want
これにはさまざまな方法がありますが 直感的に考えて
something that says a trajectory like this one in red is more
赤いトラジェクトリーについては
similar to this one in pink than it is to this one in blue,
ピンクのトラジェクトリーの方が青いトラジェクトリーよりも類似していると言えます
even though they're red and blue trajectories overlap
赤と青のトラジェクトリーが 赤とピンクよりも
more closely for a while than the red and pink ever do.
重なっている部分が多いとしても です
If you're interested in learning more,
学習をより深めたい方のために
I will include a link to a paper that discuss measures of similarity in detail,
資料中に類似性の計測についてのリンクを記載します
but once we have a measure of similarity we can use a machine learning algorithm
ただし 類似性の計測値をいったん集めれば 機械学習アルゴリズムの使用が可能となり
like agglomerative clustering or a spectral clustering to clustered these trajectories.
凝集型クラスタリングやスペクトラルクラスタリングなどによりトラジェクトリーをクラスター化します
In the case of a four-way stop intersection,
4 個所の停止交差点の場合 12 のクラスターの観測が予測できます
we would expect to see 12 clusters since at each of
つまり 各停止線では
the four stop signs cars can do one of three things: turn right,
次の 3 つのうち 1 つを実行できるためです右折
go straight or turn left.
直進 または左折です
So if we were looking at just one of those four stop signs,
この 4 つの停止線のうち 1 つだけを見てみると
we would expect to see a cluster of trajectories for left turns,
左折 直進 右折の
going straight, and turning right.
トラジェクトリーのクラスターが予測されます
Note that in some situations you may obtain even more clusters than that.
ただし ある状態ではこれよりもクラスターが多くなる場合があります
For example, if this lane is controlled by a traffic light instead of stop,
たとえば この車線が停止線の代わりに信号機により制御されていれば
your clustering algorithm will probably create twice as many clusters.
アルゴリズムのクラスター処理でおそらく 2 倍ほどのクラスターを作成します
Three of them go through the intersection without
3 つは停止することなく交差点を通過し
stopping and three of them stop at the traffic light first.
3 つはまず信号機の前で停止します
Once the trajectories have been grouped in too clusters,
トラジェクトリーがクラスターに集約されると
it is useful to define what prototype trajectories look like for each cluster.
各クラスターのプロトタイプ起動がどのようになるかの定義づけに使用できます
For the left turn cluster,
左折のクラスターでは
maybe these three trajectories are a good model.
これら 3 つのトラジェクトリーが良いモデルとなるでしょう
They provide a compact representation of what
これにより 交差点での典型的な左折挙動がどのようになるか
left turns typically look like at this intersection.
コンパクトに表現します
At this point, we have a trained model of typical car behavior at this intersection.
ここでは この交差点での典型的な車の挙動について 訓練モデルを手に入れました
The next step is to use this model on the road to actually generate predictions.
次のステップではこのモデルを使用して 道路上での実際の予測を行います